<!-- 

  projgroup.xml    FinInG package documentation
                                                                   John Bamberg
                                                                   Anton Betten
                                                                   Jan De Beule
                                                                  Philippe Cara
                                                                 Michel Lavrauw
                                                                  and Maska Law
                                                             and Michael Pauley
                                                            and Max Neunhoeffer
                                                              and Sven Reichard

  Copyright (C) 2008, University of Western Australia
                      Colorado State University
                      Lehrstuhl D fuer Mathematik
                      Ghent University
                      Vrije Universiteit Brussel

This is the chapter of the documentation describing the projective groups.

-->

<Chapter Label="diagramgeometries">
<Heading>Coset Geometries and Diagrams</Heading>
<Section>
<Heading>Preliminary version of the manual</Heading>

Suppose we have a flag-transitive incidence
geometry <M>\Gamma</M>. This means that a group <M>G</M> of
automorphisms of <M>\Gamma</M> is also given such that <M>G</M> is
transitive on the set of chambers of <M>\Gamma</M>. This implies
that <M>G</M> is also transitive on the set of all elements of any
chosen type <M>i</M>. If we consider a chamber <M>c<sub>1</sub>,c<sub>2</sub>,... ,c<sub>n</sub></M>
such that <M>c<sub>i</sub></M> is of type <M>i</M>, we can look at the
stabilizer <M>G<sub>i</sub></M> of <M>c<sub>i</sub></M>. The
subgroups <M>G<sub>i</sub></A> are 
called <E>parabolic subgroups</E> of <M>\Gamma</M>. For a
type <M>i</M>, transitivity of <M>G</M> on the elements of
type <M>i</M> gives a correspondence between the cosets of the
stabilizer <M>G<sub>i</sub></M> and the elements of type <M>i</M>
in <M>\Gamma</M>. Two elements of <M>\Gamma</M> are incident if and only
if the corresponding cosets have a nonempty intersection.

We now use the above oservation to define an incidence structure from
a group <M>G</M> together with a set of subgroups <M>G<sub>1</sub>,G<sub>2</sub>,... ,G<sub>n</sub></A>.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="DiagramOfGeometry" Arg="Gamma"/>
<Returns>The diagram of the geometry <A>Gamma</A></Returns>
<Description> 
<A>Gamma</A> must be a coset geometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="DrawDiagram" Arg="Diag,filename"/>
<Returns>Does not return anything but wirtes a file <A>filename</A>.ps</Returns>
<Description> 
<A>Diag</A> must be a diagram. Writes a file <A>filename</A>.ps in the current directory with a pictorial version of the diagram. This command uses the <Package>graphviz</Package> package which is available from http://www.graphviz.org. 
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="CosetGeometry" Arg="G,l"/>
<Returns>Returns the coset geometry defined by the list <A>l</A> of subgroups of the group <A>G</A></Returns>
<Description> 
<A>G</A> must be a group and <A>l</A> is a list of subgroups of <A>G</A>. The elements of the coset geometry are the cosets in <A>G</A> of the subgroups in <A>l</A>. Two elements are incident if and only if the corresponding cosets have nonempty intersection. 
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsIncident" Arg="ele1,ele2"/>
<Returns>true if ans only if <A>ele1</A> and <A>ele2</A> are incident</Returns>
<Description> 
<A>ele1</A> and <A>ele2</A> must be two elements in thes same coset geometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ParabolicSubgroups" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>List of parabolic subgroups defining the coset geometry <A>cg</A> </Returns>
<Description> 
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="AmbientGroup" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>the group of the coset geometry <A>cg</A></Returns>
<Description> 
<A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="Borelsubgroup" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>The Borel subgroup of de geometry <A>cg</A></Returns>
<Description> 
The Borel subgroup is equal to the stabilizer of a chamber. It corresponds to the untersection of all parabolic subgrops.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsFlagTransitiveGeometry" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>true if and only if the group <A>G</A> defining <A>cg</A> acts flag-transitively.</Returns> 
<Description> 
<A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsFirmGeometry" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>true if and only if <A>cg</A> is firm.</Returns>
<Description> 
An incidence geometry is said to be firm if every nonmaximal flag is contained in at least two chambers. <A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry. 
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsConnected" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>true if and only if <A>cg</A> is connected.</Returns>
<Description> 
A geometry is connected if and only if its incidence graph is connected. <A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsResiduallyConnected" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>true if and only if <A>cg</A> is residually connected.</Returns>
<Description> 
A geometry is residually connected the incidence graphs of all its residues of rank at least 2 are connected. <A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="StandardFlagOfCosetGeometry" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>Standard chamber of <A>cg</A></Returns>
<Description> 
The standard chamber just consists of all parabolic subgroups (i.e. the trivial cosets of these subgroups). <A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry. Maybe this function should be called StandardChamberOfCosetGeometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FlagToStandardFlag" Arg="cg,fl"/>
<Returns>element of the defining group of <A>cg</A> which maps <A>fl</A> to the standard chamber of <A>cg</A>.</Returns>
<Description> 
<A>fl</A> must be a chamber given as a list of cosets of the parabolic subgroups of <A>cg</A>. The order of the elements of the chamber should be the same as the order of the parabolics defining <A>cg</A>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="CanonicalResidueOfFlag" Arg="cg,fl"/>
<Returns>coset geometry isomorphic to residue of <A>fl</A> in <A>cg</A></Returns>
<Description> 
<A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry and <A>fl</A> must be a flag in that geometry. The returned coset geometry for a flag {giGi} is ...
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ResidueOfFlag" Arg="cg,fl"/>
<Returns>The residue of <A>fl</A> in <A>cg</A>.</Returns>
<Description> 
CHECK the back-mapping.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IncidenceGraph" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>incidence graph of <A>cg</A>.</Returns>
<Description> 
<A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry. The graph returned is a <Package>GRAPE</Package> object. Be sure the <Package>GRAPE</Package> is loaded!
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="Rank2Parameters" Arg="cg"/>
<Returns>a list of length 3.</Returns>
<Description> 
<A>cg</A> must be a coset geometry of rank 2. This function computes the gonality, point and line diameter of <A>cg</A>. These appear as a list in the first entry of the returned list. The second entry contains a list of length 2 with the point order and the total number of points (i.e. elements of type 1) in the geometry. The last entry contains the line order and the number of lines.
</Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>
</Chapter>
