<!-- 

  incidence_geometry.xml    FinInG package documentation
                                                                   John Bamberg
                                                                   Anton Betten
                                                                  Philippe Cara
                                                                   Jan De Beule
                                                                 Michel Lavrauw
                                                                Max Neunhoeffer

  Copyright (C) 2014,	Colorado State University
						Università degli Studi di Padova
						Universiteit Gent
						University of St. Andrews
						University of Western Australia
                        Vrije Universiteit Brussel

This is the chapter of the documentation describing incidence geometry
in general.

-->

<Chapter Label="incidencegeometry">
<Heading>Incidence Geometry</Heading>

We follow <Cite Key="BC2013"/> for the definitions of incidence structure and 
incidence geometry. An <E>incidence structure</E> consists of a set of elements, 
a symmetric relation on the elements and a type function from the set of
elements to an index set (i.e., every element has a ``type''). It satisfies
the following axiom: <E>(i) no two elements of the same type are incident.</E>
An incidence structure without type function is in fact a multipartite graph where
the adjacency is the incidence (so with a loop on each vertex). 

The term geometry, or incidence geometry, is interpreted broadly in this package.
Particularly, an <E>incidence geometry</E> is an incidence structure satisfying 
the following axiom: <E>(ii) every maximal flag contains an element of each type</E>.
In graph terminology, this means that every maximal clique contains an element of each type.

Thus, a projective 5-space is an incidence geometry with five types of elements: points, lines, 
planes, solids, and hyperplanes. A finite classical polar space of rank 3 is an incidence geometry
with three types of elements: points, lines, and planes. Depending on the viewpoint, the Grassmann variety
of the lines of a projective 4-space, is an incidence structure that is not an incidence geometry.<P/>

<Package>FinInG</Package> concerns itself primarily with the most
commonly studied incidence geometries of rank at least 2: projective spaces,
polar spaces, and affine spaces. Throughout, no matter the geometry, we have made the convention that
an element of type 1 is a ``point'', an element of type 2 is a ``line'', and so forth.
The examples we use in this section use projective spaces, which have
not yet been introduced to the  reader in this manual. For further information on projective spaces,
see Chapter <Ref Chap="projective_spaces"/>.<P/>

In this chapter we describe functionality that is <B>declared</B> for 
incidence structures, which does not imply that operations described here will work
for arbitrary user-constructed incidence structures. Its aim is furthermore to allow
the user to become familiar with the general philosophy of the package, using examples
that are self-explanatory. Not all details of the commands used in the examples will
be explained in this chapter, therefore we refer to the relevant chapter for the commands. These can easily be found using the index.

<Section>
<Heading>Incidence structures</Heading>

Incidence structures can be more general than incidence geometries, e.g., if they do not satisfy 
axiom (ii) mentioned above. We allow the construction of such objects. This explains one of the top level categories in 
<Package>FinInG</Package>.

<ManSection>
<Filt Name="IsIncidenceStructure" Type="Category"/>
<Description>
Top level category for all objects representing an incidence structure. 
</Description>
</ManSection>

In the following example we define an incidence structure that is not an incidence geometry. The
example used is the incidence structure with elements the subspaces contained in the line Grassmannian
of PG(4,2). This example is not meant to create this incidence structure in an efficient way, but just
to demonstrate the general philosophy.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IncidenceStructure" Arg="eles, inc_rel, type, typeset"/>
<Returns>an incidence structure</Returns>
<Description>
<A>eles</A> is a set containing the elements of the incidence structure. <A>inc_rel</A>
must be a function that determines if two objects in the set <A>eles</A> are incident. 
<A>type</A> is a function mapping any element to its type, which is a unique element 
in the set <A>typeset</A>.<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_incstruct.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Filt Name="IsIncidenceGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Description>
Category for all objects representing an incidence geometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

Lie Geometries, i.e., geometries with a projective space as ambient space, affine spaces and 
generalised polygons have their own category, which is a subcategory of <C>IsIncidenceGeometry</C>.
<ManSection>
<Heading>Main categories in <C>IsIncidenceGeometry</C></Heading>
<Filt Name="IsLieGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsAffineSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsGeneralisedPolygon" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsCosetGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Description>
Within each category, several subcategories are declared. Subcategories of <C>IsLieGeometry</C> are discussed
in Section <Ref Sect="liegeometries1"/> and subcategories of <C>IsGeneralisedPolygon</C> are discussed in Chapter <Ref Chap="gpolygons"/>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Heading>Examples of categories of incidence geometries</Heading>
<Description>
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_categories1.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="TypesOfElementsOfIncidenceStructure" Arg="inc"/>
<Attr Name="TypesOfElementsOfIncidenceStructurePlural" Arg="inc"/>
<Returns>a list of strings or integers</Returns>
<Description>
Both attributes are declared for objects in the category <C>IsIncidenceStructure</C>.
Any incidence structure has a set of types, which is usually
just the list <M>{1..n}</M>. If specific names are
given to each type, like points, lines, etc., this attribute returns the names for the
particular incidence structure <A>inc</A>. The second variant returns the list of plurals
of these names. For genericly constructed incidence structures, the names of the Elements
are also generic: elements of type 1, elements of type 2, etc.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_typesofels.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="Rank" Arg="inc"/>
<Attr Name="RankAttr" Arg="inc"/>
<Returns>rank of <A>inc</A>, an object which must belong to the categorie <C>IsIncidenceStructure</C></Returns>
<Description>
The operation <F>Rank</F> returns the rank of the incidence structure <C>inc</C>. The highest level method for
<F>Rank</F>, applicable to objects in <C>IsIncidenceStructure</C> simply refers to the attribute <F>RankAttr</F>.
In <Package>FinInG</Package>, the rank of an incidence structure is determined upon creation, when also <F>RankAttr</F>
is set.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_rank.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Elements of incidence structures</Heading>

<ManSection>
<Heading>Main categories for individual elements of incidence structures</Heading>
<Filt Name="IsElementOfIncidenceStructure" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementOfIncidenceGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementOfLieGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementOfAffineSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementOfCosetGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsSubspaceOfProjectiveSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsSubspaceOfClassicalPolarSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementOfGeneralisedPolygon" Type="Category"/>
<Description>
In general, elements of an incidence structure belonging to <C>IsIncStr</C>, are in the category
<C>IsElementOfIncStr</C>. The inclusion for different categories of geometries is followed for their elements,
with an exception for <C>IsSubspaceOfClassicalPolarSpace</C>, which is a subcategory of
<C>IsSubspaceOfProjectiveSpace</C>, while <C>IsClassicalPolarSpace</C> is not a subcategory of
<C>IsProjectiveSpace</C>.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_categories2.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ObjectToElement" Arg="inc, t, obj"/>
<Returns>an element of the incidence structure <A>inc</A></Returns>
<Description>
If <A>obj</A> represents an element of <A>inc</A> of type <A>t</A>, this operation
returns the element. An error (or no method found error) is shown
when <A>obj</A> does not represent an element of type <A>t</A>. Note that <F>ObjectToElement</F>
is a generic operation. Versions with a different argument set and even alternative operations
exist for some particular geometries to construct particular elements.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Heading>Main categories for collections of all the elements of a given type of an incidence structure</Heading>
<Filt Name="IsElementsOfIncidenceStructure" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementsOfIncidenceGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementsOfLieGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementsOfAffineSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsElementsOfCosetGeometry" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsSubspacesOfProjectiveSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsSubspacesOfClassicalPolarSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Description>
For a given incidence structure, the collection of elements of a given type can be constructed. constructed
here means that an object is returned that represents all the elements of a given type, rather than listing
them immediately, to avoid long computation times. Such an abstract object is e.g. used as a range for
In general, the collection of elements of a given type of an incidence structure belonging to <C>IsIncStr</C>,
is in the category <C>IsElementsOfIncStr</C>. The inclusion for different categories of geometries is
followed for their collection of elements of a given type, with an exception for <C>IsSubspaceOfClassicalPolarSpace</C>,
which is a subcategory of <C>IsSubspaceOfProjectiveSpace</C>, while <C>IsClassicalPolarSpace</C> is not a subcategory of
<C>IsProjectiveSpace</C>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

The object representing the set of elements of a given type can be computed using 
the general operation <F>ElementsOfIncidenceStructure</F>.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ElementsOfIncidenceStructure" Arg="inc, j"/>
<Oper Name="ElementsOfIncidenceStructure" Arg="inc, str"/>
<Returns>a collection of elements</Returns>
<Description><A>inc</A> must be an incidence structure, <A>j</A> must be
a type of element of <A>inc</A>. This function returns all elements
of <A>inc</A> of type <A>j</A>, and an error is displayed if <A>inc</A> has no 
elements of type <A>j</A>. Calling the elements (of a given type) of <A>inc</A>
yields an object in the category <C>IsElementsOfIncidenceStructure</C> (or the appropriate category
for projective spaces and classical polar spaces), which does not imply that
all elements are computed and stored. In an alternative form of this function
<A>str</A> can be one of the strings found in the list obtained by calling
<F>TypesOfElementsOfIncidenceStructurePlural(inc)</F>. E.g. for projective spaces,
``points", ``lines", ``planes" or ``solids" are the names for elements of type
1,2,3 or 4, respectively, of course
if <A>inc</A> has elements of the deduced type. <Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_elementsj.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ElementsOfIncidenceStructure" Arg="inc"/>
<Returns>a collection of elements</Returns>
<Description><A>inc</A> must be an incidence structure, then this operation returns
the collection of all elements of <A>inc</A>. Such a collection can e.g. be the range
of a geometry morphism. Note that this operation has no method for generic incidence
structures constructed using <F>Incidence Structure</F>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Heading>Short names for ElementsOfIncidenceStructure</Heading>
<Oper Name="Points" Arg="inc"/>
<Oper Name="Lines" Arg="inc"/>
<Oper Name="Planes" Arg="inc"/>
<Oper Name="Solids" Arg="inc"/>
<Returns>The points, lines, planes, solids, respectively of <A>inc</A></Returns>
<Description>
For geometries in <C>IsLieGeometry</C>, <C>IsAffineSpace</C>, and <C>IsGeneralisedPolygon</C>,
the elements of type 1,2,3,4 respectively are called usually points, lines, planes, solids, respectively.
These methods are, for such geometries, are shortcuts to <F>ElementsOfIncidenceStructure(inc,j)</F>, with <A>j</A>
equal to 1,2,3,4, respectively.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_short.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="NrElementsOfIncidenceStructure" Arg="inc, j"/>
<Oper Name="NrElementsOfIncidenceStructure" Arg="inc, str"/>
<Returns>a positive integer</Returns>
<Description><A>inc</A> must be an incidence structure, <A>j</A> must be
a type of element of <A>inc</A>. This function returns the number of elements
of <A>inc</A> of type <A>j</A>, and an error is displayed if <A>inc</A> has no 
elements of type <A>j</A>. In the alternative form of this function
<A>str</A> can be one of ``points", ``lines", ``planes" or ``solids" and the
function returns the number of elements of type 1, 2, 3 or 4 respectively, of
course if <A>inc</A> has elements of the deduced type. For geometries
in the category <C>IsLieGeometry</C>, <C>IsAffineSpace</C>, and <C>IsGeneralisedPolygon</C>,
the number of elements of a given type is known upon construction of the geometry. As such,
for these geometries, this operation requires no computing time.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_nrelements.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="Random" Arg="C"/>
<Returns>an element in the collection <A>C</A></Returns>
<Description>
<A>C</A> is a collection of elements of an incidence structure, i.e., an object in the
category <C>IsElementsOfIncidenceStructure</C>. <F>Random(C)</F> will return a random element
in <A>C</A> provided there is a method installed. The generic method will compute all elements
in <A>C</A> and return a random member from the list. For e.g. Lie geometries, more efficient
methods are installed. 
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_random.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsIncident" Arg="u,v"/>
<Oper Name="\*" Arg="u,v"/>
<Returns>true or false</Returns>
<Description>
<A>u</A> and <A>v</A> must be elements of an incidence structure.
This function returns true if and only if <A>u</A> is incident with <A>v</A>. Recall that 
<C>IsIncident</C> is a symmetric relation, while <C>in</C> is not. A method for the operation <F>\*</F> is installed, applicable to objects in <C>IsElementOfIncidenceStructure</C>. It just calls <F>IsIncident</F>.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_isincident.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
<Oper Name="AmbientGeometry" Arg="v"/>
<Returns>the ambient geometry of the element <A>v</A></Returns>
<Description>
If <A>v</A> is an element of an incidence geometry currently implemented
in <Package>FinInG</Package>, then this operation returns the ambient geometry of <A>v</A>, 
i.e., in general the geometry in which <A>v</A> was created. If an incidence structure is created with 
elements that are a subset of elements of another incidence structure, the ambient geometry
might stay unchanged.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_el_ambient.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Flags of incidence structures</Heading>

A <E>flag</E> of an incidence structure <M>S</M> is a set <M>F</M> of elements of <M>S</M> that are two by two incident. 
This implies that all elements in <M>F</M> have a different type. A flag is maximal if it cannot be extended with more elements.
<Package>FinInG</Package> provides a basic 
category <C>IsFlagOfIncidenceStructure</C>. For different types of incidence structures, methods to create a flag
can be installed. A <E>chamber</E> is a flag of size <M>n</M>, where <M>n</M> is the rank of the incidence structure. Recall that an incidence
structure is an incidence geometry if every maximal flag is a chamber. 

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FlagOfIcidenceStructure" Arg="inc, l"/>
<Returns>the flag consisting of the elements of <A>inc</A> in the list <A>l</A></Returns>
<Description>
It is checked if all elements in <A>l</A> are incident and belong to the same incidence structure. An empty list is allowed.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_flag.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="IsChamberOfIncidenceStructure" Arg="flag"/>
<Returns>true if and only if <A>flag</A> contains an element of each type</Returns>
<Description>
The incidence structure is determined by the elements.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_flag_chamber.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section Label="inc_geom:shadows">
<Heading>Shadow of elements</Heading>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ShadowOfElement" Arg="inc, v, str"/>
<Oper Name="ShadowOfElement" Arg="inc, v, j"/>
<Returns> The collection of elements of type <A>str</A> or type <A>j</A> incident with <A>v</A></Returns>
<Description>
<A>inc</A> is an incidence structure, <A>v</A> must be an element of <A>inc</A>, <A>str</A> must
be a string which is <B>the plural</B> of the name of one of the types of the elements of <A>inc</A>. For the 
second variant, <A>j</A> is an integer representing one of the types of the elements of <A>inc</A>.
This first variant relies on <F>TypesOfElementsOfIncidenceStructurePlural</F> and on a particular 
method installed for the second variant for particular incidence structures.
The use of the argument <A>inc</A> makes it flexible, i.e., if the element
<A>v</A> can belong to different incidence structures, its shadow can be different, as the second example shows.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_shadowofelement.include">
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_shadowofelement2.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ElementsIncidentWithElementOfIncidenceStructure" Arg="v, j"/>
<Returns> The collection of elements of type <A>j</A> incident with <A>v</A></Returns>
<Description>
This operation is applicable for objects <A>v</A> belonging to <C>IsElementOfIncidenceStructure</C>,
and is a shortcut to <F>ShadowOfElement(AmbientGeometry(v),v,j)</F>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ShadowOfFlag" Arg="inc, flag, str"/>
<Oper Name="ShadowOfFlag" Arg="inc, list, str"/>
<Oper Name="ShadowOfFlag" Arg="inc, flag, j"/>
<Oper Name="ShadowOfFlag" Arg="inc, list, j"/>
<Returns>The collection of elements of type <A>str</A> or type <A>j</A> incident with the elements of <A>flag</A>,
or with the elements of <A>list</A></Returns>
<Description>
Variants 2 and 4 convert <A>list</A> to a flag of <A>inc</A>, using <F>FlagOfIcidenceStructure</F>, which performs
the necessary checks. Variants 1 and 2 rely on variants 3 and 4 respectively, for which a method must be installed
for the particular incidence structure <A>inc</A>.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_shadowofflag.include">
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
<Heading>Short names for ElementsIncidentWithElementOfIncidenceStructure</Heading>
<Oper Name="Points" Arg="inc, v"/>
<Oper Name="Lines" Arg="inc, v"/>
<Oper Name="Planes" Arg="inc, v"/>
<Oper Name="Solids" Arg="inc, v"/>
<Oper Name="Points" Arg="v"/>
<Oper Name="Lines" Arg="v"/>
<Oper Name="Planes" Arg="v"/>
<Oper Name="Solids" Arg="v"/>
<Returns>The collections of elements of <A>inc</A> of respective type 1, 2, 3 and 4, 
that are incident with <A>v</A></Returns>
<Description>
It is possible that <A>inc</A> is an incidence structure where the elements of type 1, 2, 3 and 4 
respectively are not called "points", "lines", "planes", and "solids" respectively. The methods don't
check whether names are given, and are just shortcuts to the operation <F>ShadowOfElement</F>. The second variant
derives the incidence structure to be used as the ambient geometry of <A>v</A>. Please keep in mind 
that these methods are shortcuts to <F>ShadowOfElement</F>, which implies that asking e.g. <F>Lines(v)</F>
with <A>v</A> a point, will indeed return the lines incident with a point.  
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_shadowshort.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Enumerating elements of an incidence structure</Heading>
In several situations, it can be usful to compute a complete list of objects statisfying one or more conditions.
To list all elements of a given type of an incidence structure, is a typical example. <Package>FinInG</Package> 
provides functionality that is common in GAP for this purpose. 

We can either use <F>AsList</F> to get all of the elements of a projective/polar
space efficiently, or we can ask for an iterator or enumerator
of a collection of elements. The word collection is important here.
Subspaces of a vector space are not calculated on calling <F>Subspaces</F>,
rather primitive information is stored in an <F>IsComponentObjectRep</F>.
So for example

<Example>
gap> v:=GF(31)^5;
( GF(31)^5 )
gap> subs:=Subspaces(v,1);
Subspaces( ( GF(31)^5 ), 1 )
</Example>

takes almost no time at all. But if you want a random element from this set,
you could be waiting a while. Instead, the user is better off using an iterator
or an enumerator to access elements of this collection. We have
such a facility for the elements of a projective or polar space. At the moment,
we have made available iterators for projective spaces, and enumerators for polar spaces. 
We give basic examples of enumerators and iterators here. For <F>AsList</F>, we refer to 
the appropriate sections in the chapters on the particular geometries, since methods for
<F>AsList</F> always refer to the group, and make use of the package <Package>orb</Package>.

An iterator is a GAP object that gives a user friendly way to loop over all 
elements without repetition. Only three operations are applicable on an iterator:
<F>NextIterator</F>, <F>IsDoneIterator</F> and <F>ShallowCopy</F>.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="Iterator" Arg="C"/>
<Returns> an iterator for the collection <A>C</A></Returns>
<Description>
<A>C</A> is a collection of elements of an incidence structure. An iterator is returned.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_iterator.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

For a collection of elements of a given type of certain incidence structures, <Package>FinInG</Package> also provides
methods to compute an enumerator. In its simplest form, an enumerator is just a list containing all the elements of the
collection. Given any object in the list, it is possible to retrieve its number in the list (which is then just its position). 
Also, given any number between 1 and the length of the list, it is possible to get the corresponding element. For some
collections of elements of particular incidence structures, a more advanced version of enumerators is implemented. Such
an advanced version is an object containing the two functions <F>ElementNumber</F> and <F>NumberElement</F>. Such functions
are able to compute directly, without listing all elements, the element with a given number, or, conversely, compute
directly the number of a given element. Clearly, using an enumerator, it is possible to obtain a list containing all elements
of a collection.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="Enumerator" Arg="C"/>
<Returns> an enumerator for the collection <A>C</A></Returns>
<Description>
<A>C</A> is a collection of elements of an incidence structure. An enumerator is returned.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_enum.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section Label="liegeometries1">
<Heading>Lie geometries</Heading>

<ManSection>
<Heading>Main categories in <C>IsLieGeometry</C></Heading>
<Filt Name="IsProjectiveSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Filt Name="IsClassicalPolarSpace" Type="Category"/>
<Description>
Lie geometries bundle projective spaces and classical polar spaces together. In
the future, more subcategories could be added since the term ``Lie
geometry'' refers to a geometry whose automorphism group lies in some
group of Lie type. Both classes of geometries have their category, as
a subcategory of <C>IsLieGeometry</C>. 
</Description>
</ManSection>

One common fact of Lie geometries is that their elements are represented by subspaces of a vector space.
In these geometries, incidence is symmetrized set-theoretic containment. In this
section we describe methods that are declared in a generic way for (elements of)
Lie geometries. These operations are applicable to Lie geometries and related objects.

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="AmbientSpace" Arg="ig"/>
<Returns>the ambient projective space of a Lie geometry <A>ig</A></Returns>
<Description>
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_ambientspace.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="UnderlyingVectorSpace" Arg="ig"/>
<Returns>the underlying vectorspace of the Lie geometry <A>ig</A></Returns>
<Description>
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_lie_uvs.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ProjectiveDimension" Arg="ig"/>
<Returns>the projective dimension of the ambient projective space of <A>ig</A></Returns>
<Description>
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_lie_projdimension.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

Mathematically, it makes sense to implement an object representing the empty subspace, since this is typically obtained as
a result of a Meet operation, which computes the intersection of two or more elements. On the other hand, we do not consider
the empty subspace as an element of the incidence geometry. Hence, using the empty subspace as an argument of <F>IsIncident</F> (and
consequently of <F>\*</F>), will result in a ``no method found'' error.

<ManSection>
<Filt Name="IsEmptySubspace" Type="Category"/>
<Description>
Category for objects representing the empty subspace of a particular Lie geometry. Empty subspaces of different geometries will
be different objects, and have a different ambient geometry.
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Elements of Lie geometries</Heading>

Elements of a Lie geometry are constructed using a list of vectors. The methods installed for the particular
Lie geometries check whether the subspace of the vector space represents an element of the Lie geometry.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="VectorSpaceToElement" Arg="ig, v"/>
<Oper Name="VectorSpaceToElement" Arg="ig, l"/>
<Returns>the element of <A>ig</A>, represented by the subspace spanned by <A>v</A> or <A>l</A>, or returns the empty subspace.</Returns>
<Description>
The first variant of this operation takes as second argument a vector of the underlying vector space of <A>ig</A>.
Such a vector possibly represents a point of <A>ig</A>. The second variant takes as second argument a list
of vectors in the underlying vector space of <A>ig</A>. Such a list represents a subspace of the vector space. If the dimension of the subspace generated by <A>l</A> is larger than zero and strictly less than the dimension of the vector space, it is checked if the subspace
represents an element of <A>ig</A>, except when <A>ig</A> is a projective space. If <A>l</A> is a list of vectors generating the whole vector space,
then <A>ig</A> is returned if and only if <A>ig</A> is a projective space, otherwise an error is produced. An empty list is not allowed as second
argument.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_lie_vectorspacetoelement.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="UnderlyinObject" Arg="v"/>
<Returns>the vector or list of vectors representing the element <A>v</A></Returns>
<Description>
The argument <A>v</A> must be an element, so it is not allowed that <A>v</A> is the empty subspace, 
or just a projective space.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_lie_elementtovectorspace.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="\in" Arg="u,v"/>
<Returns>true if and only if the element <A>u</A> is set-theoretically contained in the element <A>w</A></Returns>
<Description>
Both arguments must be elements of the same Lie geometry. The empty subspace and a Lie geometry are also allowed
as arguments. This relation is not symmetric, and the methods for <F>IsIncident</F>
use this method to test incidence between elements. 
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_lie_in.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Heading>More short names for <F>ElementsIncidentWithElementOfIncidenceStructure</F></Heading>
<Oper Name="Hyperplanes" Arg="inc, v"/>
<Oper Name="Hyperplanes" Arg="v"/>
<Heading>Hyperplanes of an element of a Lie geometry</Heading>
<Returns>the elements of type <M>j-1</M> incident with <A>v</A>, which is an element of type <M>j</M></Returns>
<Description>
This operation is a shortcut to the operation <F>ShadowOfElement</F>, where the geometry is taken from <A>v</A>, and where 
the elements of type one less than the type of <A>v</A> are asked. <A>v</A> is allowed to be a complete projective space here, yielding the hyperplanes of that space.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_lie_hyperplanesof.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Hard wired embeddings and converting elements</Heading>

A Lie geometry, i.e., an object in the category <C>IsLieGeometry</C>, is naturally embedded 
in a projective space. This is of course in a mathematical sense. In <Package>FinInG</Package>, certain
embeddings are implemented by providing a mapping between geometries. The Lie geometries are 
<E>hard wired</E> embedded, just simply because a category containing elements of a Lie geometry, is
always a subcategory of <C>IsSubspaceOfProjectiveSpace</C>. As a consequence, operations applicable
to objects in the category <C>IsSubspaceOfProjectiveSpace</C> are by default applicable to objects
in any subcategory, so to elements of any Lie geometry. When dealing with elements of e.g. different polar
spaces in the same projective space, this yields a natural way of working with them, and investigating 
relations between them, without bothering about all necessary mappings. On the other hand, in some situations,
it is impossible to decide in which geometry an element has to be considered. An easy example is the following.
Consider two different quadrics in the same projective space. The intersection of two elements, one of each
quadric, is clearly an element of the ambient projective space. But also of both quadrics. Without extra input
of the user, the system cannot decide in which geometry to construct the intersection. To avoid complicated methods
with many arguments, in such situations, the resulting element will be constructed in the common ambient projective space.
Only in clear situations, where the ambient geometry of all elements is the same, and equal to the geometry of the 
resulting element, the resulting element will be constructed in this common geometry. We provide however conversion
operations for elements of Lie gometries.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="ElementToElement" Arg="ps, el"/>
<Oper Name="Embed" Arg="ps, el"/>
<Returns><A>el</A> as an element of <A>ps</A></Returns>
<Description>
Let <A>ps</A> be any Lie geometry. This method returns <F>VectorSpaceToElement(ps,ElementToVectorSpace(el))</F>,
if the conversion is possible. <F>Embed</F> is declared as a synonym of <F>ElementToElement</F>.<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/incgeom_lie_elementtoelement.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>
</Chapter>
