<!-- 

  intro.xml            FinInG package documentation 
 
                                                                John Bamberg
                                                                Anton Betten
                                                               Philippe Cara
                                                                Jan De Beule
                                                              Michel Lavrauw
                                                             Max Neunhoeffer
 
 Copyright (C) 2014, University of Western Australia
                     Colorado State University
                     Vrije Universiteit Brussel
                     Ghent University
                     Università degli Studi di Padova
 
 
This chapter gives a short introduction and explains the philosophy
behind the package.

-->

<Chapter Label="intro">
<Heading>Introduction</Heading>

<Section Label="philosophy">
<Heading>Philosophy</Heading>

<Package>FinInG</Package> (pronounciation: <Alt Only="LaTeX">\textipa{f\;I{}n\;I{}N}</Alt><Alt Only="HTML">f&#618;n&#618;&#331;</Alt>) is a package for computation in
Finite Incidence Geometry. It provides users with the basic tools to
work in various areas of finite geometry from the realms of
projective spaces to the flat lands of generalised polygons. 
The algebraic power of GAP is employed, particularly in its 
facility with matrix and permutation groups.

</Section>

<Section Label="overview">
<Heading>Overview of this manual</Heading>

Chapter <Ref Chap="install"/> describes the installation of the package. Chapter <Ref
Chap="examples"/> contains some extended examples to introduce the user to the basic functionality and philosophy to get started. Chapter <Ref Chap="incidencegeometry"/> contains a rigorous discription of the basic structures. This chapter can be omitted at first reading, since the set of consequent chapters is also self contained. Chapters <Ref Chap="projective_spaces"/>, <Ref Chap="projgroup"/> and <Ref Chap="polaritiesofps"/>
deal with projective spaces, projective semilinear groups and polarities of projective spaces, respectively.
In Chapter <Ref Chap="classicalpolarspaces"/> the functionality for classical polar spaces is treated and in Chapter <Ref Chap="affine"/> affine spaces and their groups are considered. <E>Geometry morphisms</E> between various geometries that are 
available in the package, are introduced and discussed in Chapter <Ref Chap="morphisms"/>. The final three chapters, <Ref Chap="varieties"/>, <Ref Chap="gpolygons"/>, and <Ref Chap="diagramgeometries"/> explain the basic functionality which is provided for algebraic varieties (in projective or affine spaces), generalised polygons, of which several models can be constructed, and finally coset geometries and diagrams.
</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>The Development Team</Heading>
This is the development team (without Anton),  meeting in St. Andrews in september 2008,
from left to right: Philippe Cara, Michel Lavrauw, Max Neunh&#246;ffer, Jan De Beule and John Bamberg
<P/>
<Alt Only="HTML">&lt;img src="devteamstasep08.jpg">&lt;/img></Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">\includegraphics[scale=0.6]{devteamstasep08.jpg}</Alt><P/>
The development team meeting again (without Anton and Max), now
in Vicenza in april 2011. from left to right: Michel Lavrauw, John Bamberg, Philippe
Cara, Jan De Beule.<P/>
<Alt Only="HTML">&lt;img src="devteamvicapr11.jpg">&lt;/img></Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">\includegraphics[scale=0.6]{devteamvicapr11.jpg}</Alt><P/>
Survivors of the first version of <Package>FinInG</Package>, enjoying a trip to Chioggia, december 2011.
<P/>
<Alt Only="HTML">&lt;img src="devteamchidec11.jpg">&lt;/img></Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">\includegraphics[scale=0.6]{devteamchidec11.jpg}</Alt><P/>
The same survivors, staring at the destiny.
<P/>
<Alt Only="HTML">&lt;img src="devteamdestiny.jpg">&lt;/img></Alt>
<Alt Only="LaTeX">\includegraphics[scale=0.6]{devteamdestiny.jpg}</Alt><P/>
</Section>


<!-- ############################################################ -->

</Chapter>
