<!-- 

  stab_orbs.xml    FinInG package documentation
                                                                   John Bamberg
                                                                   Anton Betten
                                                                  Philippe Cara
                                                                   Jan De Beule
                                                                 Michel Lavrauw
                                                                Max Neunhoeffer

  Copyright (C) 2014, University of Western Australia
                      Colorado State University
                      Vrije Universiteit Brussel
                      Ghent University
					  Università degli Studi di Padova

This is the chapter of the documentation describing the stabilisers and orbits.

-->

<Chapter Label="acts_stab_orbs">
<Heading>Orbits, stabilisers and actions</Heading>

<Section>
<Heading>Orbits</Heading>
GAP provides generic functionality to compute orbits. These functions are, generally spoken, applicable to the
groups implemented in <Package>FinInG</Package>, combined with the appropriate action functions. However, the generic
functions applied in such situations are rather time comsuming. <Package>FinInG</Package> therefore provides alternative
functions to compute orbits.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FiningOrbit" Arg="g, obj, act"/>
<Returns>The orbit of the object <A>obj</A> under the action <A>act</A> of the
group <A>g</A>.</Returns>
<Description>
The argument <A>obj</A> is either a subspace of a projective space, then combined with
the action function <F>OnProjSubspaces</F>, or a set of elements of a projective space, then
combined with the action function <F>OnSetsProjSubspaces</F>. The group <A>g</A> is a subgroup
of a collineation group of a projective space. In both cases the action function computes the action
of <A>el</A> under the group element <A>g</A>.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingorbit1.include"> 
</Example>
The second example shows the possible use of <F>FiningOrbit</F> in combination with the action function
<F>OnSetsProjSubspaces</F>. Please note that this variant is probably not the most efficient way to compute all elliptic
quadrics contained in the parabolic quadric <M>ps</M>. Experiments show that for <M>q=5</M> the second variant takes an 
unreasonable amount of time. Also note that the second argument <A>el</A> must be
a set (and therefore it might be necessary to apply <F>Set</F> on a collection of elements).
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingorbit2.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FiningOrbits" Arg="g, set, act"/>
<Returns>The orbits of the group <A>g</A> on <A>set</A> under the action of <A>act</A>.</Returns>
<Description>
The set is a set of elements of a projective space, the group <A>g</A> is a subgroup of the collineation group
of a projective space, and <A>act</A> is the function <F>OnProjSubspaces</F>.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingorbits1.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Stabilisers</Heading>

The GAP function <F>Stabilizer</F> is a generic function to compute stabilisers of one object (or sets or tuples etc. of objects)
under a group, using a specified action function. This generic function can be used together with the in <Package>FinInG</Package>
implemented groups and elements of geometries. However, computing time can be very long, already in small geometries.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_example1.include"> 
</Example>

The packages <Package>GenSS</Package> and <Package>orb</Package> required by <Package>FinInG</Package> provide 
efficient operations to compute stabilisers, and <Package>FinInG</Package> provides functionality to use 
these operations for the particular groups and (elements) of geometries.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FiningStabiliser" Arg="g, el"/>
<Returns>The subgroup of <A>g</A> stabilising the element <A>el</A></Returns>
<Description>The argument <A>g</A> is a group of collineations acting on the element <A>el</A>, being a
subspace of a projective space (and hence, all elements of a Lie geometry are allowed as second argument).
This operation relies on the <Package>GenSS</Package> operation <F>Stab</F>.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingstabiliser.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FiningStabiliserOrb" Arg="g, el"/>
<Returns>The subgroup of <A>g</A> stabilising the element <A>el</A></Returns>
<Description>The argument <A>g</A> is a group of collineations acting on the element <A>el</A>, being a
subspace of a projective space (and hence, all elements of a Lie geometry are allowed as second argument).
This operation relies on some particular <Package>orb</Package> functionality.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingstabiliserorb.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

A small example shows the difference in computing time. Clearly the <F>FiningStabiliserOrb</F> is the fastest 
way to compute stabilizers of one element.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_timing1.include"> 
</Example>

Computing the setwise stabiliser under a group is possible using <F>Stabilizer</F>. Not suprisingly, the
computing time can also be very long.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_setwisegeneric.include"> 
</Example>

The package <Package>GenSS</Package> provides an efficient operation to compute setwise stabilisers, 
and <Package>FinInG</Package> provides functionality to used these <Package>GenSS</Package> operation 
for the particular groups and (elements) of geometries.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FiningSetwiseStabiliser" Arg="g, els"/>
<Returns>The subgroup of <A>g</A> stabilising the set <A>els</A></Returns>
<Description>The argument <A>g</A> is a group of collineations acting on the element <A>el</A>, being a
subspace of a projective space (and hence, all elements of a Lie geometry are allowed as second argument).
The argument <A>els</A> is a set of elements of the same type of the same Lie geometry, the elements are all in 
the category <C>IsSubspaceOfProjectiveSpace</C>. The underlying action function is assumed to be
<F>OnProjSubspaces</F>
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingsetwisestabiliser.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

A small example shows the difference in computing time. 
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_timing2.include"> 
</Example>

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Actions and nice monomorphisms revisited</Heading>

GAP provides generic functions to compute action homomorphisms and their images for arbitrary groups. These
functions are applicable on the projective groups implemented in <Package>FinInG</Package>.

<ManSection>
<Heading>Action functinos</Heading>
<Func Name="OnProjSubspaces" Arg="el, g"/>
<Func Name="OnProjSubspacesExtended" Arg="el, g"/>
<Func Name="OnSetsProjSubspaces" Arg="set, g"/>
<Returns>a element of a Lie geometry</Returns>
<Description>
Let <A>el</A> be an element of any Lie geometry, and <A>g</A> an element of a projective group
acting on the elements of the ambient Lie geometry of <A>el</A>. Then then <F>OnProjSubspaces</F>
will return simply the image of <A>el</A> under <A>g</A>. When <A>g</A> is an element of the correlationcollineation group
of a projective space, <F>OnProjSubspacesExtended</F> returns the image of <A>el</A> under <A>g</A>. Finally,
when <A>set</A> is a set of elements of a Lie geometry, <F>OnSetsProjSubspaces</F> returns the set of images
under <A>g</A>. <F>OnProjSubspaces</F> is also explained in <Ref Sect="proj:onprojsubspaces"/>,
<F>OnProjSubspacesExtended</F> is also explained in <Ref Sect="proj:onprojsubspacesextended"/>.
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Heading>Generic GAP functions</Heading>
<Oper Name="ActionHomomorphism" Arg="g, S, act"/>
<Oper Name="Action" Arg="g, S, act"/>
<Description><A>g</A> is a projective group, <A>S</A> is a set or a collection of elements, <A>act</A>
is an action function. <F>Action</F> simply returns <F>Image(hom)</F>, if <A>hom</A> is the result
of <F>ActionHomomorphism</F>. The examples are self-explanatory.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_action1.include">
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="NiceMonomorphism" Arg="group"/>
<Returns>A group homomorphism</Returns>
<Description>

</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="NiceObject" Arg="group"/>
<Returns>A group homomorphism</Returns>
<Description>

</Description>
</ManSection>

<ManSection>
<Attr Name="IsHandledByNiceMonomorphism" Arg="group"/>
<Returns>A group homomorphism</Returns>
<Description>

</Description>
</ManSection>

Some more examples, also explaining <F>SetParent</F>.

</Section>

</Chapter>