<!-- 

  stab_orbs.xml    FinInG package documentation
                                                                   John Bamberg
                                                                   Anton Betten
                                                                  Philippe Cara
                                                                   Jan De Beule
                                                                 Michel Lavrauw
                                                                Max Neunhoeffer

  Copyright (C) 2013, University of Western Australia
                      Colorado State University
                      Vrije Universiteit Brussel
                      Ghent University
					  Università degli Studi di Padova

This is the chapter of the documentation describing the stabilisers and orbits.

-->

<Chapter Label="acts_stab_orbs">
<Heading>Actions, stabilisers and orbits</Heading>

<Section>
<Heading>Stabilisers</Heading>

The GAP function <F>Stabilizer</F> is a generic function to compute stabilisers of one object (or sets or tuples etc. of objects)
under a group, using a specified action function. This generic function can be used together with the in <Package>FinInG</Package>
implemented groups and elements of geometries. However, computing time can be very long, already in small geometries.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_example1.include"> 
</Example>

The packages <Package>GenSS</Package> and <Package>orb</Package> required by <Package>FinInG</Package> provide 
efficient operations to compute stabilisers, and <Package>FinInG</Package> provides functionality to used 
these operations for the particular groups and (elements) of geometries.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FiningStabiliser" Arg="g, el"/>
<Returns>The subgroup of <A>g</A> stabilising the element <A>el</A></Returns>
<Description>The argument <A>g</A> is a group of collineations acting on the element <A>el</A>, being a
subspace of a projective space (and hence, all elements of a Lie geometry are allowed as second argument).
This operation relies on the <Package>GenSS</Package> operation <F>Stab</F>.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingstabiliser.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>


<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FiningStabiliserOrb" Arg="g, el"/>
<Returns>The subgroup of <A>g</A> stabilising the element <A>el</A></Returns>
<Description>The argument <A>g</A> is a group of collineations acting on the element <A>el</A>, being a
subspace of a projective space (and hence, all elements of a Lie geometry are allowed as second argument).
This operation relies on some particular <Package>orb</Package> functionality.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingstabiliserorb.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

A small example shows the difference in computing time. Clearly the <F>FiningStabiliserOrb</F> is the fastest 
way to compute stabilizers of one element.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_timing1.include"> 
</Example>

Computing the setwise stabiliser under a group is possible using <F>Stabilizer</F>. Not suprisingly, the
computing time can also be very long.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_setwisegeneric.include"> 
</Example>

The package <Package>GenSS</Package> provides an efficient operation to compute setwise stabilisers, 
and <Package>FinInG</Package> provides functionality to used these <Package>GenSS</Package> operation 
for the particular groups and (elements) of geometries.

<ManSection>
<Oper Name="FiningSetwiseStabiliser" Arg="g, els"/>
<Returns>The subgroup of <A>g</A> stabilising the set <A>els</A></Returns>
<Description>The argument <A>g</A> is a group of collineations acting on the element <A>el</A>, being a
subspace of a projective space (and hence, all elements of a Lie geometry are allowed as second argument).
The argument <A>els</A> is a set of elements of the same type of the same Lie geometry, the elements are all in 
the category <C>IsSubspaceOfProjectiveSpace</C>. The underlying action function is assumed to be
<F>OnProjSubspaces</F>
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_finingsetwisestabiliser.include"> 
</Example>
</Description>
</ManSection>

A small example shows the difference in computing time. 
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "../examples/include/stab_orbs_timing2.include"> 
</Example>

</Section>
</Chapter>